<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Decaying Foundations on Decaying Foundations </title>
      <generator uri="https://gohugo.io">Hugo</generator>
    <link>https://decaying.systems/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
    
    <updated>Sun, 22 Mar 2020 16:28:22 EET</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>[000] It Has Already Begun</title>
      <link>https://decaying.systems/posts/000-it-has-already-begun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Mar 2020 16:28:22 EET</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://decaying.systems/posts/000-it-has-already-begun/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the first installment of &amp;lsquo;Decaying Foundations&amp;rsquo; series. It opens up in the world, which resembles ours very much. A parallel universe, if you will. The year is unknown, but judging from the technology and people, it is somewhere around 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This short mix offers a glimpse in that world, where multiple contributing factors slowly introduce instability and chaos in various regions. It happens gradually, almost undetected. Seemingly random things tend to be discarded until it&amp;rsquo;s clear that it definitely isn&amp;rsquo;t. Mistakes are made and quickly compounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One might think they are not affected by any of this when it is happening on the other side of the screen. Riot happening on the other side of the window isn&amp;rsquo;t real. Until that very defining moment, when window glass cracks and the sound from the street fills the void. That&amp;rsquo;s when the realization that it&amp;rsquo;s too late comes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay alert!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Link to the recording&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://soundcloud.com/palanga_street_radio/decaying-foundations-000-it&#34;&gt;https://soundcloud.com/palanga_street_radio/decaying-foundations-000-it&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What This Is All About</title>
      <link>https://decaying.systems/posts/what-this-is-all-about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://decaying.systems/posts/what-this-is-all-about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You might have stumbled upon this site by randomly browsing the internet, or following a link from one of the mixes accompanying this site and be wondering: &amp;ldquo;ok, so what this is all about?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;lsquo;Decaying Foundations&amp;rsquo;&lt;/strong&gt; is a fusion of fictional stories and electronic music used to create and shape the alternative world, which resembles ours so much. A reflections from the (im)possible future, if you will. It&amp;rsquo;s about the world and its everyday dystopias we&amp;rsquo;re experiencing right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not a coincidence - most of the fiction about the future is not about the future at all - the basis of fears, uncertainty, and challenges are from the present it&amp;rsquo;s written in. Building imaginative worlds using a mixture of mechanisms is the exercise of understanding our own, sometimes in entirely new ways &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every short story about events transpired in this oppressive world is accompanied by the sounds selected and mixed after the story is written. The particular strand of futurism in that world is the primary aspect of the musical aesthetic of selected sounds. All of the mixes and accompanying stories are exclusively published through the &lt;a href=&#34;https://palanga.live&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Palanga Street Radio&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; platform on a monthly schedule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One might find these stories uncomfortable - the only thing that can be promised is that it&amp;rsquo;s not going to be an enjoyable, easy-listening experience. At least, it might leave you with a thought: how does the future we want to live in looks like?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
