<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Decaying Foundations on Decaying Foundations </title>
      <generator uri="https://gohugo.io">Hugo</generator>
    <link>https://decaying.systems/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
    
    <updated>Thu, 25 Jun 2020 19:59:22 EEST</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>[003] The Voices That Werent</title>
      <link>https://decaying.systems/posts/003-the-voices-that-werent/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jun 2020 19:59:22 EEST</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://decaying.systems/posts/003-the-voices-that-werent/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The bleak morning light was seeping in through the molded metal grid of the old, abandoned drainage tube. It slowly diluted the darkness filling the vast cold and wet space. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t the light that would trigger another cycle in your circadian rhythm system, gently nudging you to wake up. Above the ground, dull and repetitive surface expanded way beyond the grey line of the horizon in that grim light. The land ruptured in a few places and hasn&amp;rsquo;t seen water for a long time. Small scanty patches of flora were scattered in random patterns. The rain would not help it, anyway. Acidic rains were falling from time to time, slowly ruining water streams and forests. The rain wasn&amp;rsquo;t that dangerous to people, but the air was full of elements causing it. And your lungs full of it would eventually cause serious problems. The air felt like a thick prickly cloth hanging in there.
The thing is that the majority of the commonWealth&amp;rsquo; population living in the megacities would not see any of it. Most people traveling between megacities would use the hyper tube, which was the fastest, cheapest - and safest - option to go. Almost all of the hyper tube infrastructure was underground, built to last. Limited overground interchange stations offered &amp;ldquo;amusement bars&amp;rdquo; and other amenities to the weary travelers. All of the smart surfaces, including walls and windows, usually projected everything except the view outside stations - but most of them would not care anyway - the majority of their time was spent in their VR overlays. The same thing applied when traveling via air - windows were long replaced by smart panels projecting anything but the devastated landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;She was afraid to move.&lt;/em&gt; The silence inside the drain was deafening. After a few hours in there, imagination starts playing its games, and you start &amp;ldquo;hearing&amp;rdquo; various things— primarily when deeply ingrained beliefs and tribal myths already fuel your imagination. She tried to stretch her back as quietly as possible and shivered when the sound of screeching outer shell reverberated through the tube. She was pretty sure she heard some indiscernible click or scratch in the distance and immediately froze. Few minutes stretched out like a few hours. Only the thumping heartbeat inside gave some reference about the passing time.
Nothing. She stood up as quietly as possible and started moving through the dark tunnel, putting one boot after another into the stinking water and deliberately moving towards the exit latch. Finally, she approached.
She put back thick gloves on, pulled on a heavy hoodie with the mask, completely covering the face, and started to climb. Once outside, she squatted behind the fabbed think wall, as grey as the rest of the landscape, and watched. The same way they&amp;rsquo;ve all been taught countless of times before, so it became a mantra. The problem was that it was getting harder to notice them before its too late. They&amp;rsquo;ve been adapting to the environment quite quickly. Once designed and built for search and rescue missions, this versatile platform of robots rapidly became the first line of defense in the commonWealth. The thing is that with the last industrial revolution and some of the events in the past completely changed the landscape. Interlocked distribution and manufacturing chains spinning across the globe were slowly replaced by more regional and locally running manufacturing centers. Some of them were nearby the megacities, servicing them. Some of them were moved farther away. That massive campaign to move rurally living people to the cities finally paid off - it took over 50 years and few iterations to get it right, but you might call it a great success. All the noisy, inconvenient, and usually harmful manufacturing could then be moved outside of &amp;ldquo;the city rings.&amp;rdquo; Until increasing radiation and pollution levels become alarmingly clear. Unless, of course, no one takes care to look at the metrics. Maybe, even on purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another problem was The Invisibles. While they were ulterior to most of the population, they still existed. Being pushed out to the outskirts and trying to live with what you have was one thing. But the deeply rooted hate for the System could&amp;rsquo;ve been explained by ever-growing pollution outside in most of the areas and being systemically oppressed further down the road. They were still being seen as a problem. Now that there was no leverage to influence their behavior, it was the question of keeping all that infrastructure safe, as it became one of the targets for The Invisibles. Fab plants had useful materials and printers you could use to build stuff you need. Some of the smaller plants were of &amp;ldquo;lights out&amp;rdquo; style, managed remotely. Larger ones had a lot of personnel for the assurance of smooth operations.
There was a vast network of drones and self-sufficient ground robots, to guard and defend these objects operated by the Makers tribe. Most of the Invisibles clung to each other, forming clusters in places that were somewhat still habitable. The primary focus was just to survive.
There was another side of the spectrum - groups trying to get into the megacities, damaging and stealing worthy equipment, trying to hijack drones and other autonomous maintenance droids, creating as much as possible chaos and fear around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She was sitting on the edge of a drained pool. The PA interface she was trying to boot, wasn&amp;rsquo;t showing any signs of life. Occasionally, she would stop and listen after a few moments of getting back to the interface.
&amp;ldquo;It was a huge mistake,&amp;rdquo; - she sighed, looking for the multitool in the bag. It all started when a group of the Invisibles broke into one of the fab houses in the area. It seemed like a routine operation: stage a service disruption somewhere else, rerouting maintenance droids to that location, get in, take what you need, get out. Complications started to arise when the operation began. One of their groupies broke the leg, and they needed to operate with fewer people. That meant less loot to take home.
Another problem was that the intelligence signals they&amp;rsquo;ve got were not accurate. When they finally got into the house, they found two members of Makers, who were trying to debug some manufacturing pipeline issue. Things escalated quite quickly from there, and Invisibles took maintenance people hostages. Red alerts started firing by the systems humming thousands of kilometers away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Little did they know that their fate was already decided. At least it should&amp;rsquo;ve been. It was still a less known &amp;lsquo;feature&amp;rsquo; of the System. As events unfolded, some random people in the three megacities received amber type alert, which meant &amp;lsquo;immediate action.&amp;rsquo; It was one of the &amp;lsquo;ethical dilemma&amp;rsquo; type of things, where the problem and few choices have been presented to you. Most of them inattentively responded - &amp;lsquo;eliminate the threat.&amp;rsquo; Almost immediately after that, threat response units were given the instructions to operate. The majority of the respondents didn&amp;rsquo;t give a second thought about it - it was perceived as one of those research projects.
A drone, flying high above in the sky, changed the course and started flying towards a new target.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;What&amp;rsquo;s the problem?&amp;rdquo; - a voice on the other end sounded irritated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Sir, sorry to bother you, but I think we have another case &amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; - NOC person handling the case responded sharply.
&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s already the third one, this week!&amp;rdquo; - an irritated voice now sounded twice as loud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I know, sir, and it&amp;rsquo;s not all of it - the second drone we&amp;rsquo;ve sent - it&amp;rsquo;s doing nothing as well, just hovering o&amp;hellip;&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;A second one?!?&amp;rdquo; - he was abruptly cut off by the irritated voice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Yes sir, initial diagnosis showed no problems, but we thought it might be a case of the jamming again; thus, we&amp;rsquo;ve sent another drone to the same location to complete the quest. It seems that operators cannot take over manual control, the same as in other cases.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I see. What are the possible targets in the area?&amp;rdquo; - the voice became calm, somewhat tired.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Well, that&amp;rsquo;s the problem, sir, I think this case is a bit different than the others. There are no other active commonWealth properties nearby on the ground &amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;How far it could still fly?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The border is 4 hours away, any of the strike drones could reach it.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Target lock both of the drones w/ manually managed units and let me know when you&amp;rsquo;re ready.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Roger, sir.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of the drones were hovering over the fab plant high above in the sky. The Invisibles hiding inside knew that, as well as the Maker tribe members as well. They&amp;rsquo;ve heard rumors before; thus, it was an intense atmosphere inside the building. Everyone in this building knew how ruthlessly they could be hunted down and incinerated. Completely vanished from the surface. Problem solved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the drones suddenly did a U-turn facing the second drone. Two rapid subsequent flashes blicked in the dark sky. The second drone, hit at least once, started to lose height&amp;rsquo;. After a few minutes, it hit the ground near the fab house it was hovering over. The attacking drone did another turn and started to climb up, flying away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She remembered quite clearly how confused everyone one was, double-checking the measurements of the instruments. Nobody expected to get away without a fight, and now here it is. The sky is clear. Of course, there were guard robots, but they still had some time while the grid network will be re-enabled in the area.
The squad started to move quickly. Everyone knew their role in this; thus, everything was smooth. They loaded the vehicles with everything they possibly could, briefly stopping only the question arise what they&amp;rsquo;re going to do with the Makers. After a short debate, they&amp;rsquo;ve been gagged, roped, and put into the vehicles&amp;rsquo; backs. One of them was a decoy, sent across the wasteland to distract the ones after them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;She still remembered that loud, sharp metal screeching sound, and everything after that suddenly becomes blurry. What happened afterward?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the approximately same time, the drone reaches its destination. Hovering above the shoreline, it was waiting for its target. A ship was leaving the busy port nearby, and slowly moving towards the gate to the open sea.
Heavily loaded, it would travel to its destination with the commonWealth goods. Except, it won&amp;rsquo;t reach it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Link to the recording:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://soundcloud.com/palanga_street_radio/decaying-foundations-003-the&#34;&gt;https://soundcloud.com/palanga_street_radio/decaying-foundations-003-the&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[002] The Fantasy Of Opting Out</title>
      <link>https://decaying.systems/posts/002-the-fantasy-of-opting-out/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2020 08:36:22 EEST</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://decaying.systems/posts/002-the-fantasy-of-opting-out/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s the darkest hour of the night. It&amp;rsquo;s quiet, as it can get in the megapolis. From the bird&amp;rsquo;s eye view, it seemed like a sleepy and inert organism; some movement over here, some bleep and whiz over there. The robot dog patrolling the area suddenly darts across the lightly illuminated garden to stop nearby giggling teenagers on a bench to start citing information about safety protocols. Still giggling, they slowly get up and move towards the illuminated gate. Giant maintenance robots lazily following invisible lines, waiting for new commands from the c&amp;amp;c center.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High above the sky and hidden behind the impenetrable layer of clouds, this tranquil moment was flying a drone. Almost undetectable, it was slowly pushing through the dark sky. Measurements were taken, probe signals sent, reading back from the mesh sensor networks. And it wasn&amp;rsquo;t alone. The sky was full of silent watchers. If one could visualize the signal paths and information they were exchanging, the dark dome would suddenly be brightly lit, with alternating beams shooting across the sky, like a thick pulsing web.
The city wasn&amp;rsquo;t sleeping either. Massive complex systems deployed on the ground were receiving and processing all of these beacons. And it was hungry for more. Way much more. You could almost hear the whispers in the air, or was it just the hot air coming out of the chiller pipes? At the break of the dawn, the drones would go up in the sky, blending into the indistinguishable greyness. The city would cheerily fill with the noise, starting to breath more rhythmically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ &amp;hellip; ]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adam took a sip of the old smoky whiskey or, rather, a skillfully made surrogate of it. The real thing was a very rare artifact nowadays. Only the richest could afford it, and even amongst those circles, it remained a highly valued trophy. The industry found its way to the people&amp;rsquo;s hearts by providing a replacement, which successfully deceived your taste receptors, making you perform a theatrical appearance on &amp;ldquo;how it was done during the old&amp;rsquo; good days.&amp;rdquo;
He looked at the fake old red brick wall, which was part of the &amp;ldquo;amusement bar&amp;rdquo; he was in, and sighed, feeling the burn in his mouth slowly expanding into his trachea. He was sitting alone in the small lobby area of this &amp;ldquo;bar,&amp;rdquo; where only a quietly whirring bar robot was keeping him company. There were two small privacy cubicles, but they were empty as well. On the other side of the room, there was a door. That door opened to a very long corridor lit by bright neon light strips. When your eyes adjusted, you could see small hatches on both sides. Lots of them, at least three rows up, across the whole corridor. A hatch would open up to a somewhat claustrophobic space, where you could lie on a warm cushy surface. The rounded walls were pulsing glow.
You could even feel the warm radiance going through your fingers when touched. That&amp;rsquo;s where people immersed themselves in various experiences, being overloaded in the impossible sensory overloads. That was the escapist&amp;rsquo; Eden. Pain or pleasure, whatever made you tick. Industrial grade.
The explosive growth in people living in these megacities during the commonWealth boom years reshaped the city, and how many millions of people live. Like many cities, this one was home to neverending high-rise housing blocks, where apartments are often tiny, and it wasn&amp;rsquo;t possible to put those advanced bulky capsules in very cramped spaces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adam was still gazing at the brick wall. He wondered about the times when people would go to the dark abandoned warehouses to do the strange dance rituals being continuously assaulted by sheer sonic bombs from enormous speaker systems. They danced their problems away surrounded by darkness, they said. He couldn&amp;rsquo;t tell whether thas was just propaganda or a real thing. Anyway, it was about &amp;ldquo;them&amp;rdquo; - outsiders, and you couldn&amp;rsquo;t tell for sure. Nowadays, nobody was going anywhere. &amp;lsquo;I could use some of that insanity right now&amp;rsquo; - he caught himself thinking. &amp;ldquo;We are now thirty years into an uncontrolled social experiment, run by The Engineering, that has broken a great deal for a few. The autocratic tendencies shown are horrifying, but it feels like there is no way out &amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; - he was pointing at the robot&amp;rsquo;s interface with a hand holding the glass. &amp;lsquo;Ah, shucks, what&amp;rsquo;s the point, just get me another&amp;rsquo; - he said, putting the empty glass on the counter. That distinctive sound of glass hitting top of the bar seemed to stir up the robot, which swiftly moved it&amp;rsquo;s hand around and started executing the order. It was one of the older models, not the ones with a next-gen stack that looked human and were always connected to the grid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He knew that he was tracked very precisely by the humongous organism, like everyone else. Adam knew that he was on camera when he left the apartment: while in the hallway and the elevator of his building, while passing shops in the street and waiting at crosswalks, while in the hyperloop station and on the train — and all that just coming here. A montage of nearly every move he makes in the city outside his apartment could be assembled, and each step retraced. But that would hardly be necessary: his personal assistant, in the course of its ordinary operation of seeking base stations to keep him connected as he walks across the city, provided a constant log of the position and movements. And it&amp;rsquo;s keeping pretty verbose tabs on all his grid activity as well.
Any time he spends in the &amp;ldquo;black zones&amp;rdquo; without grid reception can also be accounted for: specialized high-def cameras in the hyperloop station would capture his face and ID him in a matter of few milliseconds. His built-in badge produces a record of his entry into the building in which he works. His cramped apartment is part of a smart-grid program, spikes in his electricity usage can reveal exactly when he is up and around, turning on lights and ventilation fans and using the kitchen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adam knew too well that there was no easy way to simply get away from it. Like, can&amp;rsquo;t people just opt out of systems with which we disagree? Some thought that if you drop below the rating threshold and become Invisible, you&amp;rsquo;re out. But it was merely deceiving act - the system could still track you, it just ignored you completely, to force you out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Engineering played an essential role in it as it allowed for a competitive environment for high-tech companies to be created.  The official agenda was to make everything more efficient and available for everyone, making lives more comfortable. One can&amp;rsquo;t do that by not measuring what they&amp;rsquo;re about to manage. &amp;ldquo;Data-driven&amp;rdquo; became a chant of the decade. Soon everyone was collecting everything they possibly could. Data analysis capabilities were somewhat weak, but there was plenty of storage, for &amp;ldquo;we&amp;rsquo;ll figure this out later&amp;rdquo; type of things. Soon enough, a real-time market, where one could dump all their collected data they couldn&amp;rsquo;t use otherwise appeared - highest paying bidder would grab that - that&amp;rsquo;s their problem now. How might it be used? All we care about is how many credits we&amp;rsquo;re getting for it &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adam took another sip. A lot of time passed until he joined the dots and understood that lots of data collection and analysis solutions were coming from a single entity. Sure, it was a vast network of separate companies. But they all were connected. Even the symbol of infinity on the consortium logo radiated that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was heavily supported by Engineering. &amp;ldquo;Infinity&amp;rdquo; was instrumental at making sure that police and other responders had the decent tech to work with. Crime rates went down, effectiveness went up. At least that&amp;rsquo;s what the metrics showed. In some cases, it made total sense: they were providing body cameras that learn what people look like and surveillance cameras that can track people&amp;rsquo;s movements, automated license plate readers, etc. Using artificial intelligence to analyze data from the ever-growing networks of surveillance cameras helped agencies do their jobs more efficiently — it saved a lot of time sifting for evidence, and allowed easy redaction of people&amp;rsquo;s faces from footage when released to the public. Authorities used artificial intelligence to identify suspects in all kinds of crimes, from shoplifting to murders. Combining multiple methods have been used to recover stolen goods when they couldn&amp;rsquo;t be tracked otherwise, solve drive-by shootings, and track down the serials. That was always prised by the commonWealth leadership - look at the crime numbers.  It makes a difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The light outside never changes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the fastest-growing surveillance markets were public schools. &amp;ldquo;Infinity&amp;rdquo; has taken advantage of that trend, with other umbrella companies winning contracts to install state-of-the-art video networks, which outfitted newest schools with cameras that can automatically track people through rooms and hallways based on their appearance. Ubiquitous surveillance at schools was sold to everyone by using fear and partially as a promise to make students more engaged and productive as a result of participating in such a system. The quick experiment, exploding into a comprehensive project. It turned scattered cameras into mass surveillance machines that allowed companies and agencies to use them to rewind someone&amp;rsquo;s life. The technology scanned classrooms every 30 seconds, and recorded students&amp;rsquo; facial expressions, categorizing them into happy, angry, nervous, confused, or upset. The system also recorded student actions such as writing, reading, raising a hand, and sleeping at a desk. The &amp;ldquo;intelligent classroom behavior management system,&amp;rdquo; also recorded students&amp;rsquo; presence, and faces were used for identification and inventory purposes. Over time it became ubiquitous. &amp;ldquo;Infinity&amp;rdquo; subsidiaries were providing solutions to track the activity of the employees as well. &amp;lsquo;Working more productively&amp;rsquo; was another chant of the decade. Conversations and movements would be monitored. Smart badges would know if you were talking, whether you were sitting or standing, or in proximity to the other people. Combined with the calendar data and virtual desktop snapshots from your workspace, it would give enough data points to determine where you&amp;rsquo;re and what you&amp;rsquo;re doing at any given moment of your working day.&lt;br&gt;
People knew that they were being measured continuously against invisible objectives, and it was easier to comply than to revolt. Of course, there was a movement against it, but it was weak, almost invisible. Ambient tracking was so prevalent that it was tough to flip the switch and disappear. Quite the opposite - by hiding, you were standing out in all of the noise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surely, the data harvested was anonymized in strict conformity with the most fashionable data protection laws. But that didn&amp;rsquo;t matter anymore. Long gone were days when you wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be subjected to facial recognition on the street, or tagged on social media or your voice captured by a mic of always-on assistant installed somewhere.
Ambient privacy was incredibly hard to protect. It extended into social and public spaces outside the reach of privacy laws.  A considerable portion of people&amp;rsquo;s lives has been brought under the magnifying glass of software maintained by The Engineering. Nobody complained about the always-on smart baby monitors, which would save those brittle lives, or the ambient noise monitors, which would notify the landlord company about illegal gatherings and noise level violations in their properties and tag offenders. These were useful applications, slowly mutating into something else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then the argument changed that ambient privacy being a relic of an older world was a pleasant but inessential feature in this brave new world. Social norms had changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The cry for help dissolved into the void without being answered&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The infrastructure of mass surveillance was already too complicated, and the tech oligopoly too powerful. Even experts didn&amp;rsquo;t have a full picture of the surveillance economics, partly because its beneficiaries were so tight-lipped, and in part, because the entire arrangement was in flux.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ &amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To what extent is living in a surveillance-enveloped world compatible with freedom? What are the consequences of raising a generation of children whose every action feeds into a database? What does it mean to be manipulated from an early age by machine learning algorithms that adaptively learn to shape our behavior?
That&amp;rsquo;s not the conversation &amp;ldquo;Infinity&amp;rdquo; wanted to have.
Their comprehensive vision is of a world with no ambient privacy, heavily influenced by the &amp;ldquo;few&amp;rdquo; companies that can manage to accrue information at a planetary scale. The goal is to further consolidate their control over the algorithmic panopticon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ &amp;hellip; ]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adam&amp;rsquo;s thoughts were abrupted by the SEV-1 alert in his vision field. His personal assistant stopped responding to the commands as well. That could mean only one thing. He turned his back and saw himself in the mirrored helmet visor worn by a person wearing a black tactical response uniform. A ghostly pale lemniscate was glowing on his identification patch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Just in time,&amp;rdquo; - whispered Adam to himself. He made the mental effort to &amp;ldquo;touch&amp;rdquo; the blinking bubble in his vision field. It took a couple seconds to become green. That meant that the identity of both parties was confirmed. That didn&amp;rsquo;t mean much for Adam. It was a way to verify someone&amp;rsquo;s identity before continuing to interact, and commonWealth&amp;rsquo; Registry was the authoritative source to provide means for the verification process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;You need to come with us, sir&amp;rdquo; - it seemed that he heard a low-pitch metallic voice inside his skull. He knew that there is no point in resisting or running away. And the funny thing was, he was one of them. The exemplar, one of the few to be chosen to join The Engineering circle. Adam operated in few different squads until he landed into the Observability tribe, where he was spending the rest of the cadence.
More he did in there, more he felt helpless, confused, and angry. At first, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t that bad. The scale of everything was sheer and the information fragmented; thus, it was hard to get the bigger picture. And the perks of being part of Engineering kept him distracted enough not to think about it. But as time passed, it was hard to ignore the sickening agenda on the table, which landed nearly unnoticeable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He slowly stood up and followed them into the daylight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The city isn&amp;rsquo;t sleeping&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Link to the recording:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://soundcloud.com/palanga_street_radio/decaying-foundations-002-the&#34;&gt;https://soundcloud.com/palanga_street_radio/decaying-foundations-002-the&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[001] Algorithms of Oppression</title>
      <link>https://decaying.systems/posts/001-algorithms-of-oppression/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Mar 2020 16:33:42 EET</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://decaying.systems/posts/001-algorithms-of-oppression/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The second installment of the series brings us a decade back before events in the opening part took place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bunch of neighboring countries formed a Union, known as commonWealth, where technocracy was prevalent. It was a response to ever-growing economic challenges, changing social norms, and rising immigration. Globalization and rising automation have made life more insecure for the working and middle classes, with privileged people concentrating in the cities, leaving rural areas less habited. A blend of such problems, technocratically minded people getting politically involved, and the influx of capital were few reasons for creating a very fertile ground for later events. There was a quickly rising tide of companies attacking transportation, financial, health care, and other domains. They moved quickly and without much hesitation. The age, perfectly described by the phrase &amp;lsquo;Software is eating the world.&amp;rsquo; Most of the fields suffered from systemic pathologies, stagnated by the inability to reinvent themselves. Thus, it&amp;rsquo;s not surprising that a secret recipe to success was a tiny bit of the radical vision, hyper-focus on the user experience, and sheer boldness. Quickly, these fields were reliving the Renaissance. Combined with the technological advancements of that age, this approach to solve problems rapidly became ubiquitous, practically being dissolved in the fabric of reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It gave birth to a movement of what later became known as The Engineering. A clique of privileged, highly educated people working in those corporations, maintaining that foundational layer, supporting the needs of society. &amp;ldquo;disrupting the world&amp;rdquo; as they would define it. All of these systems became interconnected and ubiquitous; thus, the stakes were high - you can&amp;rsquo;t let just anyone doing that kind of job. What was previously known as the meticulous interview process, later became an almost fanatical, religious experience. It started just with a few companies. Still, as they quickly became centers of gravity, these approaches of letting in only certain people inside their circle quickly became cargo culted everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Engineering was responsible for creating an always-on, connected wherever-you-go experience, which was a very unusual thing for most of the people at the time. The moment you woke up, your personal assistant would set all things in motion. Music, known to work up your mood, would start playing, breakfast would be prepared while you&amp;rsquo;re in the shower, and the transport was about to be dispatched to pick you up. That was all decided and orchestrated by the system in massive data centers humming thousands of kilometers away. It seemed like a dream finally coming true - everything was running so smoothly, all of these systems interacting together, exchanging the gold of the age - the information. You never worried about scheduling doctor&amp;rsquo; appointments. The PA would do that for you and immediately would create a bidding request in the realtime healthcare market if any of your vitals would show that something is wrong. In the same way, you never worried anymore about your favorite products not being available in the grocery shop. All these data points about your daily life would be silently fed into enormously complex systems, feeding supply chains humming away, providing things you needed. Carefully curated newsfeeds at your fingertips, continuously changing music playlists, being constructed in the realtime according to your mood, and other reported metrics. Augmented reality and advanced VR sets became ubiquitous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing is that this omnipresent techno dream still couldn&amp;rsquo;t exist without people. If you weren&amp;rsquo;t part of the prestigious clique, like Engineering, you were an aiding citizen. The system would schedule tasks for you to accomplish in exchange for the so-called citizen points. It quickly became the essence of being a part of this society. The higher the rating - the more doors would be open, less time spending in the queues, and other pleasantries were readily available for you. One day, you might be flagged to do a so-called &amp;lsquo;cold drive.&amp;rsquo; It was a practice of driving in the self-driving car in supervising mode after a major version of firmware update. It was one of those things introduced in the transportation system after so many accidents happened before. The system would choose someone with enough skills and experience to supervise a car doing a routine self-test drive. At least you would get points for driving that car around for a while until it would switch to &amp;lsquo;autonomous&amp;rsquo; mode again. If you did really well, the system might reward you with enough points to claim your &amp;lsquo;VR-cation.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was quite a phenomenon. Highly immersive VR and custom-tailored entertainment systems were evolving, and pornography wasn&amp;rsquo;t an exception. It was a perfect dance of feedback loops - systems generating a highly immersive experience, making sure your internal feedback loop would be triggered, overwhelming with dopamine in your system, reading back the reaction, and then adapting the whole experience to it. Most people couldn&amp;rsquo;t resist it - and they didn&amp;rsquo;t. One could spend 3 days being fully immersed in this almost never-ending stimulation until you&amp;rsquo;d be brought back to be a helping citizen. In the end, it was about pleasing system enough to get back the same favor. Most people abided by the rules, as it was very convenient. It had a side effect of people regulating themselves to behave. If you ever tried shitting in the street of the Engineering heaven, that would not go very well for you. Nobody would shout or do immediate harm to you, but invisible forces would set in motion to recalculate your points. After such a stint, your own residence might not let you in with that points balance. It was a noble idea to reinforce people on good merits with the help of unbiased algorithms, only to slowly become a grim nightmare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People definitely went under the threshold. All the time. At first, the system would try to alter newsfeeds and other aspects of life to try to counterbalance that behavior to reinforce doing good deeds. Still, over time, other things happened - some noticed that you would gradually become ignored by the system. People wouldn&amp;rsquo;t see you in their augmented reality environments, your messages would stop being routed, and you wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be served in the shop or the restaurant, because you would stop existing in the system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s how Invisibles became part of this reality. At first, they tried to live in the cities - it quickly became a very harsh environment for such people. They were slowly pushed to the outskirts, disappearing from the cities altogether. It was a stark reality out there as well. Due to pollution and various diseases, everything was contaminated, and most of the wealthier people were clustering in the cities, where it was safe. But to some extent, being in complete social isolation seemed far worse than catching up a gut dissolving bug and slowly becoming a bloody puddle somewhere in the bushes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It all started as a dream to build an efficiently running environment, where everyone would be treated fairly. The dream was still there, being blindly pushed by the charming leaders, but the circumstances already changed. Systems maintained by the Engineering were so ubiquitous, it managed pretty much every aspect of our lives. A few, well-executed experiments seemed to successfully prove a point that it&amp;rsquo;s possible to create self-sustainable and objective systems, which would reflect all our needs. And when the snowball was already rolling, it was already too late. Even Engineering couldn&amp;rsquo;t understand the implications their software or algorithm change would cause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Link to the recording:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://soundcloud.com/palanga_street_radio/decaying-foundations-001&#34;&gt;https://soundcloud.com/palanga_street_radio/decaying-foundations-001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[000] It Has Already Begun</title>
      <link>https://decaying.systems/posts/000-it-has-already-begun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Mar 2020 16:28:22 EET</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://decaying.systems/posts/000-it-has-already-begun/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the first installment of &amp;lsquo;Decaying Foundations&amp;rsquo; series. It opens up in the world, which resembles ours very much. A parallel universe, if you will. The year is unknown, but judging from the technology and people, it is somewhere around 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This short mix offers a glimpse in that world, where multiple contributing factors slowly introduce instability and chaos in various regions. It happens gradually, almost undetected. Seemingly random things tend to be discarded until it&amp;rsquo;s clear that it definitely isn&amp;rsquo;t. Mistakes are made and quickly compounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One might think they are not affected by any of this when it is happening on the other side of the screen. Riot happening on the other side of the window isn&amp;rsquo;t real. Until that very defining moment, when window glass cracks and the sound from the street fills the void. That&amp;rsquo;s when the realization that it&amp;rsquo;s too late comes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay alert!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Link to the recording&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://soundcloud.com/palanga_street_radio/decaying-foundations-000-it&#34;&gt;https://soundcloud.com/palanga_street_radio/decaying-foundations-000-it&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What This Is All About</title>
      <link>https://decaying.systems/posts/what-this-is-all-about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://decaying.systems/posts/what-this-is-all-about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You might have stumbled upon this site by randomly browsing the internet, or following a link from one of the mixes accompanying this site and be wondering: &amp;ldquo;ok, so what this is all about?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;lsquo;Decaying Foundations&amp;rsquo;&lt;/strong&gt; is a fusion of fictional stories and electronic music used to create and shape the alternative world, which resembles ours so much. A reflections from the (im)possible future, if you will. It&amp;rsquo;s about the world and its everyday dystopias we&amp;rsquo;re experiencing right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not a coincidence - most of the fiction about the future is not about the future at all - the basis of fears, uncertainty, and challenges are from the present it&amp;rsquo;s written in. Building imaginative worlds using a mixture of mechanisms is the exercise of understanding our own, sometimes in entirely new ways &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every story about events transpired in this oppressive world is accompanied by the sounds selected and mixed after the story is written. The particular strand of futurism in that world is the primary aspect of the musical aesthetic of selected sounds. All of the mixes and accompanying stories are exclusively published through the &lt;a href=&#34;https://palanga.live&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Palanga Street Radio&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; platform on a monthly schedule. Tune in on last Thursday of the month, at 1700 GMT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One might find these stories uncomfortable - the only thing that can be promised is that it&amp;rsquo;s not going to be an enjoyable, easy-listening experience. At least, it might leave you with a thought: how does the future we want to live in looks like?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
