<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Decaying Foundations</title>
    <link>https://decaying.systems/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Decaying Foundations</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2020 20:19:22 +0300</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://decaying.systems/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>[007] The Omen of Faith</title>
      <link>https://decaying.systems/posts/007-the-omen-of-faith/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2020 20:19:22 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://decaying.systems/posts/007-the-omen-of-faith/</guid>
      <description>Long years passed by. The eternity of collective suffering. Over time, the collective became less aware of its existence, while the weak links linking its cells gradually vanished away.
For over 300 years, everything succumbed and seemingly hindered. The world became weirdly still - at least on the surface. The only sure thing was that uneasy stillness in the air. But not for long. It took decades for the poisoned, scarred Earth to take a deep breath and start recovering, which seemed like an impossible thing to do at that time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[006] The Ode To The Fallen Cities</title>
      <link>https://decaying.systems/posts/006-the-ode-to-the-fallen-cities/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Sep 2020 16:15:22 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://decaying.systems/posts/006-the-ode-to-the-fallen-cities/</guid>
      <description>The time passing after the Great Drone Wars was dreadful. In few years after that, everyone pretty much vanished from the surface. Lucky ones took the shelter or ran away as far as they could. Well, at least they tried. The ones who weren&amp;rsquo;t that fortunate were condemned for the painful permanence on the surface.
The air was hot and still thick with the ashes, and there were no signs of it getting cooler anytime soon.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[005] A Thousand Paths (Not) Taken</title>
      <link>https://decaying.systems/posts/005-a-thousand-paths-not-taken/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Aug 2020 20:51:22 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://decaying.systems/posts/005-a-thousand-paths-not-taken/</guid>
      <description>The dark wind blew over the seemingly dead plains. The air was thick with the ashes of the deceased. The black and impenetrable cloth of smoke and weary clouds encompassed everything, reaching the horizon.
The small flakes of the ashes were silently landing on the thick, muddy dirt. Little puddles scattered across the dark landscape of sickening colors. Gravel on the ground was all black with occasional lambent pieces - usually a scanty barbed wire or metal plate.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[004] The Givings of Fire</title>
      <link>https://decaying.systems/posts/004-the-givings-of-fire/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2020 20:15:22 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://decaying.systems/posts/004-the-givings-of-fire/</guid>
      <description>He was walking around the cluster of sparse bushes, growing in what seemed utterly random order.
A distant sound of the cascading waterfall was somewhat soothing. He liked coming down here and wandering around for hours, lost in the maze of his thoughts. He was thirstily breathing in all that air, even if now it was stale. Supporting infrastructure was already shut down; it was just a matter of time when everything else collapses on itself.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[003] The Voices That Werent</title>
      <link>https://decaying.systems/posts/003-the-voices-that-werent/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jun 2020 19:59:22 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://decaying.systems/posts/003-the-voices-that-werent/</guid>
      <description>The bleak morning light was seeping in through the molded metal grid of the old, abandoned drainage tube. It slowly diluted the darkness filling the vast cold and wet space. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t the light that would trigger another cycle in your circadian rhythm system, gently nudging you to wake up. Above the ground, dull and repetitive surface expanded way beyond the grey line of the horizon in that grim light. The land ruptured in a few places and hasn&amp;rsquo;t seen water for a long time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[002] The Fantasy Of Opting Out</title>
      <link>https://decaying.systems/posts/002-the-fantasy-of-opting-out/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2020 08:36:22 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://decaying.systems/posts/002-the-fantasy-of-opting-out/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s the darkest hour of the night. It&amp;rsquo;s quiet, as it can get in the megapolis. From the bird&amp;rsquo;s eye view, it seemed like a sleepy and inert organism; some movement over here, some bleep and whiz over there. The robot dog patrolling the area suddenly darts across the lightly illuminated garden to stop nearby giggling teenagers on a bench to start citing information about safety protocols. Still giggling, they slowly get up and move towards the illuminated gate.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[001] Algorithms of Oppression</title>
      <link>https://decaying.systems/posts/001-algorithms-of-oppression/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Mar 2020 16:33:42 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://decaying.systems/posts/001-algorithms-of-oppression/</guid>
      <description>The second installment of the series brings us a decade back before events in the opening part took place.
A bunch of neighboring countries formed a Union, known as commonWealth, where technocracy was prevalent. It was a response to ever-growing economic challenges, changing social norms, and rising immigration. Globalization and rising automation have made life more insecure for the working and middle classes, with privileged people concentrating in the cities, leaving rural areas less habited.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[000] It Has Already Begun</title>
      <link>https://decaying.systems/posts/000-it-has-already-begun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Mar 2020 16:28:22 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://decaying.systems/posts/000-it-has-already-begun/</guid>
      <description>This is the first installment of &amp;lsquo;Decaying Foundations&amp;rsquo; series. It opens up in the world, which resembles ours very much. A parallel universe, if you will. The year is unknown, but judging from the technology and people, it is somewhere around 2020.
This short mix offers a glimpse in that world, where multiple contributing factors slowly introduce instability and chaos in various regions. It happens gradually, almost undetected. Seemingly random things tend to be discarded until it&amp;rsquo;s clear that it definitely isn&amp;rsquo;t.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What This Is All About</title>
      <link>https://decaying.systems/posts/what-this-is-all-about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://decaying.systems/posts/what-this-is-all-about/</guid>
      <description>You might have stumbled upon this site by randomly browsing the internet, or following a link from one of the mixes accompanying this site and be wondering: &amp;ldquo;ok, so what this is all about?&amp;rdquo;
&amp;lsquo;Decaying Foundations&amp;rsquo; is a fusion of fictional stories and electronic music used to create and shape the alternative world, which resembles ours so much. A reflections from the (im)possible future, if you will. It&amp;rsquo;s about the world and its everyday dystopias we&amp;rsquo;re experiencing right now.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>